Guide to the Carnegie Endowment for International Peace records,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series IV: Division of International Law
  - Subseries IV.H: Report on Teaching of International Law, 1913-1921
    The volumes in this subseries are indexed. (Indices are available in RBML. Electronic versions of the indices are in preparation.) )
    - 1913 (Volume 394-395)
    - 1921 (Volume 396-397)
- Series V: Conferences and Institutes
  (14 boxes)
  This series comprises the Endowment's files on the national and international conferences and institutes in which it participated or maintained an interest, as well as those it organized or funded. The files reflect the work of all three divisions and the secretary's office of the Endowment.
  - Advisory Committee on the Research on International Law, 1937 (Box 204)
  - America Japan Student Conference (Second and Fourth), 1934-1937 (Box 204)
  - America's Commitments for Peace, Conference on, 1945 (Box 204)
  - American Committee of the House of Commons, 1937 (Box 204)
  - American International Relations, National Conference on, 1926 (Box 204)
  - American Scientific Congresses
    - Seventh, 1931 (Box 205)
    - Eighth
      - 1939-1940 April (Box 205)
      - 1940 June -Dec, 1942 (Box 206)
  - American States, Eighth International Conference of (Lima, Peru), 1938 (Box 206)
  - American States, Ninth International Conference of, 1945 1948 (Box 206)
  - American Studies in Higher Education in Great Britain, Conference on, 1938-1939 (Box 206)
  - Anglo-American Conference for Professors of History, 1923 (Box 206)
  - Associaciones de Comercio y Produccion, Conferencia Americana de (Montevideo), 1940-1941 (Box 206)
  - Boston Conference on Distribution, 1946-1947 (Box 207)
  - British and American Students Conference at the University of Michigan, 1931 (Box 207)
  - British and American Professors of English, Conference of, 1923 (Box 207)
  - Carnegie Endowment Consultative Group Conferences, 1944 (Box 207)
  - Chatham House-International Chamber of Commerce Joint Economic Survey, 1934-1935 (Box 207)
  - China Conference, 1930 (Box 207)
  - Columbia Conference, 1935 (Box 207)
  - Congress of Comparative Law, 1932-1934 (Box 207)
  - Dawes Plan, London Conference on, 1924 (Box 207)
  - Debates in Puerto Rico, 1929 (Box 207)
  - Disarmament Conference (Radio Addresses), 1932 (Box 208)
  - Documents Distribution, Second and Third Conferences on, 1947-1948 (Box 208)
  - Dumbarton Oaks Peace Conference, 1944-1945 (Box 208)
  - Earlham Institute of Foreign Affairs, 1935-1937 (Box 208)
  - Economic Conference, 1932 (Box 209)
  - Education and Citizenship, National Conference on (McGill University), 1926 (Box 209)
  - Educational Reconstruction in Central and Eastern Europe, Institute on, 1943 (Box 209)
  - Institute of Current World Affairs, 1926 (Box 209)
  - Institute of European Relations, 1930 (Box 209)
  - Institute of Government: University of Omaha, 1939 (Box 209)
  - Institute of Human Relations: University of North Carolina, 1938 (Box 209)
  - Institute of International Relations, University of Oklahoma, 1942 1945 (Box 209)
  - Institute of Public Affairs, Athens, Georgia, 1931-1937 (Box 209)
  - Institute of Public Affairs, Southern Methodist University, 1935-1947 (Box 209)
  - Institute of Public Affairs, University of Virginia, 1929-1943 (Box 210)
  - Institute of Statesmanship: Rollins College, 1929 (Box 210)
  - Institute of World Affairs (Arlington, VA), 1940 (Box 210)
  - Institute of World Affairs, Maine, 1935 (Box 210)
  - Inter-American Academy of Comparative and International Law (Havana), Second Annual Session of the, 1946-1947 (Box 210)
  - International Administration, Conference on Experience in (Washington), 1943 (Box 210)
  - International Congress of Psychology (Ninth), 1929 (Box 210)
  - International Congress (Sixth) of Genetics and the Third International Congress of Eugenics, 1930-1932 (Box 210)
  - International Geological Congress (Sixteenth), 1932 (Box 210)
  - International Peace Campaign, 1936 (Box 210)
  - International Problems and Relations (Briarcliff Manor, N.Y.), National Conference on, 1926 (Box 211)
  - International Studies Conference, 1946 (Box 211)
  - Interorganizational Conference, 1946-1948 (Box 211)
  - Kansas Institute (Third) of International Relations, 1938 (Box 211)
  - Kyoto Conference, 1930 (Box 211)
  - League of Nations Secretariat, Exploratory Conference on the experience of the, 1942-1943 (Box 211)
  - London Conference, 1934-1935
    - 1934-1935 Jan (Box 211)
    - 1935 Feb-March (Box 212)
  - London meeting, 1939 (Box 212)
  - Michigan Law Conference, 1937 (Box 212)
    See also: University of Michigan. Seventh Summer Session.
    - 1937 Jan-May (Box 212)
    - 1937 June -1938 Jan (Box 213)
  - National Council of Scientific, Professional, Art and White Collar Organizations, 1945-1946 (Box 213)
  - National Farm Institute, 1947 (Box 213)
  - National Organizations for the United Nations, Conference of, 1946 (Box 213)
  - Pan American Child Congress (Fifth), 1926 (Box 213)
  - Pan American Congress of Mining, Engineering and Geology, 1942 (Box 213)
  - Pan American Scientific Congress (Third), Lima, 1924 (Box 213)
  - Pan Pacific Science Congress (Third), 1926 (Box 213)
  - Paris Conference for the Study of Cultural Relations Among Nations, 1948 (Box 213)
  - Peace Institute, Oberlin College, 1935-1937 (Box 213)
  - Princeton Meeting on Latin America, 1941 (Box 213)
  - Public Affairs Forum: Berea College, 1942 (Box 213)
  - Public Affairs Institute Genesco, New York 1944 (Box 213)
  - Public Affairs Institute of Kansas City, 1941 (Box 214)
  - Public Forum, Omaha, Nebraska, 1942-1945 (Box 214)
  - Saint Louis Institute on Peace Problems, 1944-1945 (Box 214)
  - Scientific Spirit and Democratic Faith, Inc., Conference on the, 1946 (Box 214)
  - Seminars on Problems of United States Foreign Policy, Dartmouth College, 1947 (Box 214)
  - South Carolina Conference of Social Work, 1947 (Box 214)
  - Southern Students Conference on International Relations, 1925 (Box 214)
  - Summer Institute of Politics, Bethlehem, Pa. 1942-1943 (Box 214)
  - Teachers of International Law, 7th Conference of, 1937 1941-1942 (Box 214)
  - Teachers of International Law and Related Subjects, Eighth Conference of, 1946-1947 (Box 214)
  - Textile Conference at Washington, 1937 (Box 215)
  - Training for International Administration, Conference on, 1943-1945 (Box 215)
  - United Nations Conference on International Organizations
    The Endowment was invited by the Secretary of State to send representatives to serve as consultants to the American delegation at the United Nations Conference on International Organization held at San Francisco, April 25-June 26, 1945 at which the Charter of the United Nations was drafted and signed.
    - General, 1945 May -Sept (Includes photos) (Box 215)
    - Notes, drafts, proposals, resolutions (Box 215)
    - Press releases (Box 215)
    - Meeting minutes, 1945 May (Box 216)
    - Printed matter (Box 216)
  - University of Michigan, Ann Arbor. Seventh Summer Session on International Law, 1937-1938 (Box 217)
    See also: Michigan Law Conference (this series) and Series VI. Organizations. Summer sessions (box 263.4)
  - Washington Conference. Special Committee for Peace and Law throughout the UN, 1947 (Box 217)
  - World Organizations, Institute on, 1942 (Box 217)
  - World Peace Conference (F. Joliot-Curie), 1950 (Box 217)
  - World University Convocation, 1943 (Box 217)
  - Young Adults on Citizenship and Public Affairs of the New York State Community Service Council Cornell University (Ithaca, New York), Third Annual State Conference of, 1944 (Box 217)
- Series VI: Organizations
  (52 boxes)
  The Endowment cooperated with many organizations (governmental and non-governmental, national and international) to foster greater and more pervasive understanding of international relations and to increase support for international laws, cooperation, and accommodation.
  These files represent the work of all three divisions and the secretary's office of the Endowment. They consist of correspondence, memoranda, minutes, agenda, press releases, pamphlets, periodicals, and other publications.
  See also Series III.B. Topical volumes.
  - Academie de Droit International de la Haye (Academy of International Law at the Hague), 1926-1927 1937 (Box 217)
  - The Academy of Political Science, 1945 (Box 217)
  - Academy of World Economics, 1949 (Box 217)
  - Albanian-American School of Agriculture, 1931 (Box 217)
  - The Allied Circle, 1944-1945 (Box 217)
  - American Academy of Arts and Letters, 1929-1932 (Box 217)
  - American Academy of Political Science, 1931 (Box 217)
  - The American Academy of Political and Social Science, 1936-1924 1947-1948 (Box 217)
  - American Arbitration Association, 1926 (Box 217)
  - American Art Association, 1923 (Box 217)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1933 (Box 217)
  - American Association of Museums, 1929 (Box 217)
  - American Association of University Women, 1929-1930 (Box 217)
  - American Bar Association, 1937-1947
    - 1937-1942 (Box 217)
    - 1943-1947 (Box 218)
  - American Chinese Committee of the Mass Education Movement, 1946-1948 (Box 218)
  - American Committee in Geneva, 1926-1939 (Box 218)
  - American Council on Education, 1925-1926 1936 1943-1950
    - 1925-1926 1936 (Box 218)
    - 1943-1950 (Box 219)
  - American Council of Foreign Bond Holders, 1933 (Box 219)
  - American Council of Learned Societies, 1941-1946 (Box 219)
  - American Council on Public Affairs, 1939 (Box 219)
  - American Country Life Association, 1943-1944 (Box 219)
  - American Farm School, 1932 (Box 219)
  - American Federation of Labor, 1944-1945 (Box 219)
    This file includes material regarding a statement of foreign policy issued by Commission to Study the Organization of Peace, the AFL National Post War Forum in NYC, the Dumbarton Oaks Proposal, and the magazine article "Building a Lasting Peace" by James T. Shotwell.
  - American Friends Service Committee, 1946-1947 (Box 220)
  - The American Foundation, Inc., 1924-1933 (Box 220)
  - American Geographical Society, 1947 (Box 220)
  - American Historical Association, 1938-1939 (Box 221)
  - American Institute of International Law, 1945 (Box 221)
  - American Institute in Prague, 1925-1933 (Box 221)
    Includes personal reports on political situation in and around Germany.
  - American Japan Student Conference, 1938 (Box 221)
  - American Labor Conference on International Affairs, 1944-1945 (Box 221)
  - American Museum of Natural History, 1925 (Box 221)
  - American National Committee to Cooperate with the Committee on International Cooperation of the League of Nations, 1926 (Box 221)
  - American National Livestock Association, 1941 (Box 221)
  - American Peace Society, 1926 1929 1935-1939 1944-1947 (Box 221)
    The APS had as its purpose the advance of the general use of conciliation, arbitration, judicial methods, and other peaceful means of avoiding and adjusting differences among nations. The file includes the publications "Pan Americana", "The New Panamericana", as well as the Pan American Peace Conference manuscript by Jame M. Yepes and a Statement on Dumbarton Oaks Proposal by Butler.
  - American Permanent International Exposition, 1926 (Box 221)
  - American Relief for France, Inc., 1946-1947 (Box 221)
    ARF was a voluntary organization whose purpose was to raise funds for French rehabilitation and promote American-French friendship through cultural exchanges, libraries, and other means. Correspondence in these files deals mainly with appointment of the Associate Director of CEIP to the Board of Directors of ARF, Canteen Centers in Relief Areas, fund raising, meeting announcements and minutes, planning for a hospital in Saint-Lo, France, and copies of the bulletin "American Aid to France."
  - The American Russian Institute, 1943-1945 (Box 221)
  - American School in Japan, 1920-1932 (Box 222)
  - American Slav Institute at Prague, 1925-1926 (Box 222)
  - American Society of International Law, 1945-1949 (Box 222)
  - American Union for Concerted Peace Efforts, 1939 (Box 222)
  - American University Graduate School, 1930 (Box 222)
  - American University Union, 1926-1946 (Box 222)
  - The American-Yugoslav Society, Inc, 1927 (Box 222)
  - Americans United for World Organization, Inc, 1944-1945 (Box 222)
  - Amerika Institut, 1926-1939 (Box 222)
  - The Association of the Bar of the City of New York, 1928-1929 (Box 222)
  - Association des Mouvements Internationaux de Solidarite pour le Rapprochment Entre les Peuples, 1947 (Box 222)
  - Association Yougoslave de Droit International, 1937 (Box 223)
  - Austrian League for the United Nations, 1946 (Box 223)
  - Austro-American Institute of Education, 1926 1929 1930-1938 (Box 223)
  - Atlantic Union Committee, 1949 (Box 224)
  - Bank for International Settlements, 1930-1931 (Box 224)
  - Baltimore and Ohio Railroad, 1949 (Box 224)
  - La Bienvenue Francaise, 1923-1931 (Box 224)
  - The Brookings Institution, 1947 (Box 224)
  - Brooks-Bright Foundation, 1929 (Box 224)
  - Byrd Associates, 1937 (Box 224)
  - Camp Fire Girls, 1931 (Box 224)
  - Canada-United States Committee on Education, 1946 (Box 224)
  - Catholic Council for International Relations, 1937 (Box 224)
  - The Central and Eastern European Planning Board, 1942-1945 (Box 224)
  - Centre Francais de Documentation, 1939 (Box 224)
  - Character Education Institution, USA, 1927 (Box 224)
  - Chinese Students' Christian Association in North America, 1944-1947 (Box 225)
  - Chinese Students Committee on Allowances, 1925 (Box 225)
  - Church Peace Union, 1925 1938 1943-1947 (Box 225)
  - Citizens for World Cooperation, 1943-1944 (Box 225)
  - Comite de Celebration de 80 Anniversaire de M. Paul Milioukov, 1939 (Box 225)
  - Committee on the Consideration of Inter-Governmental Debts, 1933-1934 (Box 225)
  - Committee on Cultural Relations with Latin America, 1930-1936 (Box 225)
  - Committee on Educational Publicity, 1929 (Box 225)
  - Committee on the Study of Teaching Materials on Inter-American Subjects of the American Council on Education, 1944 (Box 226)
  - Committee for the Tenth Anniversary of League of Nations, 1929 (Box 226)
  - Common Council for American Unity, 1942-1947 (Box 226)
  - The Cooperative Education Society, 1946 (Box 226)
  - Council on Foreign Relations, 1927-1947
    - 1927-1939 (Box 226)
    - 1940-1947 (Box 227)
  - Council for a Lasting Peace, 1943-1944 (Box 227)
  - Council on World Affairs, 1937-1947 (Box 228)
  - Denver Central Committee, 1945-1946 (Box 228)
  - Denver Citizens for Victory, 1945 (Box 228)
  - Detroit Committee for the Study of the Organization of Peace, 1943 (Box 228)
  - Deutsche Hochscule Fur Politik, 1926 1932 (Box 228)
  - Economic Club of Detroit, 1937 (Box 228)
  - Economic Policy Committee, 1938-1941 (Box 228)
  - Includes correspondence regarding the National Farm Institute and photographs. (Box 228)
  - Emergency Committee to Save the Jewish People of Europe, 1944 (Box 228)
  - English-speaking Union of the United States, 1925-1938 (Box 229)
  - Experiment in International Living, 1947 (Box 229)
  - Farmers Educational and Cooperative Union, 1941 (Box 229)
  - Federacion de Estudiantes de Habla Espanola, 1917 (Box 229)
  - Federated American Chambers of Commerce of the Near East, Inc., 1925 (Box 229)
  - Foreign Policy Association, 1926-1946 (Box 229)
  - Foundation de L'Alliance Francaise, 1923 (Box 229)
  - France-Amerique, 1921-1923 (Box 230)
  - Franco-American Bulletin, 1923 (Box 230)
  - Free World Association, 1944 (Box 230)
  - General International Students Organizations, 1929-1930 (Box 230)
    This file includes correspondence regarding the Second World Youth Conference, British and American Students Conference on International Affairs, Sixth Annual British and Dominions Conferences, Federation Universitaire International pour la SDN, Confederation Internationale des Etudiants, Intercollegiate Disarmament Council, National Student Federation of the USA, International Student Hospitality Association, and the Geneva School of International Studies.
  - Geneva Federation, 1925 (Box 230)
  - The Geneva School of International Studies, 1926 (Box 230)
  - Greater N.Y. Federation of Churches, 1936-1943 (Box 230)
  - The Girl Scouts, Inc., 1941-1946 (Box 230)
  - Grotius Society and International Law Association, 1936-1948 (Box 230)
  - Indiana Committee for Victory, 1943-1945 (Box 230)
  - Indiana Council on International Relations, 1929-1936 (Box 231)
  - Institute Balkanique, 1935 (Box 231)
  - Institute of International Education, 1919 1923-1946
    - 1919 1923-1929 (Box 231)
    - 1930-1946 (Box 232)
  - Institute of Pacific Relations, 1925-1950
    - 1925-1927 Aug (Box 233)
    - 1927 Sept-1928 (Box 234)
    - 1929-1930 Sept (Box 235)
    - 1930 Oct-1933 (Box 236)
    - 1934-1938 (Box 237)
    - 1939-1950 (Box 238)
    - American Council
      - Minutes, 1928-1931 (Box 238)
      - Publications and reports (Box 239)
      - Clippings, 1927-1931 (Box 239)
  - Institute of Public Affairs, 1928-1929 (Box 239)
  - Institute on World Organization, 1941-1947 (Box 239)
  - Instituto Argentino de Derecho International, 1936-1937 (Box 239)
  - Instituto Italiano di Diritto Internazionale, 1937 (Box 239)
  - Instituto Panamericano, 1935 (Box 239)
  - Inter-American Bar Association, 1940-1944 (Box 239)
  - Inter-American Students Conference, 1935-1936 (Box 239)
  - International Alliance of Women, 1946-1947 (Box 239)
  - International Arbitration League, 1923 1926 1936-1947 (Box 240)
  - International Assembly of Women, 1947 (Box 240)
  - International Chamber of Commerce, 1925 (Box 240)
  - International Committee of Historical Sciences, 1930 (Box 240)
  - International Committee for the Study of European Questions, 1946 (Box 240)
  - International Commission on Folk Arts, 1934 1939 1943 (Box 240)
  - International Federation of League of Nations Societies, 1937 (Box 240)
  - International Film Foundation, 1946 (Box 240)
  - International House, New York City, 1925 1927 (Box 240)
  - International Industrial Relations Association, 1931 (Box 240)
  - International Migration Service, 1925 (Box 240)
  - International Montessori Association, 1936 (Box 240)
  - International Moral Education Conference, 1923-1930 (Box 240)
  - International Organizations, 1939-1942 (Box 240)
    This file includes correspondence regarding plans for post-war reconstruction with the following organizations: Institute of Sociology, International Cooperative Women's Guild, Associated Country Women of the World, International Shipping Conference, International Bureau of Education, International Cooperative Alliance, Inter-federation of Trade Unions, International Federation of University Women, Alliance Universelle Pour L'Amite, Internationale par les Eglise, World Power Conference, and London International Assembly.
  - International Peace Campaign, 1937-1938 (Box 241)
    Directed by Viscount Cecil of Chelwood
  - International People's College, 1949-1950 (Box 241)
  - Interparliamentary Union, 1925-1949 (Box 241)
  - Italy-America Society, 1925 (Box 241)
  - Japan Society, 1926 (Box 241)
  - La Nueva Democracia, 1931 (Box 241)
  - League to Abolish War, 1925 (Box 241)
  - The League to Enforce Peace, 1917-1919 (Box 241)
  - The League of Nations and the United Nations, 1923-1949
    Includes correspondence regarding the U.S. government, Miss Florence Wilson (League of Nations librarian), the exploratory conference on the experience of the League of Nations Secretariat, the cataloging system of C.E. Walton (1930). The files also include reports and meeting agendas, Budget Study of the United Nations (1947) meeting reports, newspaper clippings, and material relating to the United Nations Economic, Scientific, and Cultural Organization (1947), the National Conference on the United Nations (January 4. 1949), the Interim Commission on Food and Agriculture (1943-1945), the Ship Orientation Program (1946), the United Nations Commission on Human Rights (1947), the United Nations Information Offices, the Ad Hoc Committee on Consultative Non-Government Organizations (1948), and the Interim Committee of Consultative Non-Government Organizations.
    - 1923-1935 (Box 241)
    - 1936-1937 1943-1947 Feb (Box 242)
    - 1937 March-1949 (Box 243)
    - 1950 (Box 244)
  - Conference on the experience of the League of Nations Secretariat, 1942-1944 (Box 244)
  - International Institute of Intellectual Cooperation, 1946 (Box 244)
  - Sweetser, Arthur, 1926-1938 (Box 245)
  - League of Nations Association (1923-1944) / American Association for the United Nations (1945-1947)
    The League of Nations Association distributed informational material and operated high school essay contests and model assembly programs. These files include meeting notices and minutes, reports, memoranda on foreign policy questions, policy statements, copies of speeches, press releases, and itineraries of various speakers. The files also contain several publications, including "A Short History of the League of Nations", "The Powers of Congress in the Governing of Foreign Affairs" by Smith Simpson, "The Farmer's Stake in World Peace" by Donald Blaisdell, and "International Relations for Secondary Schools" by Hilda M. Watters.
    - 1924-1931 Sept (Box 245)
    - 1931 Oct-1935 (Box 246)
    - 1936-1939 1943-1945 (Box 247)
    - 1946-1947 (Box 248)
  - League of Nations Non-Partisan Association, 1927 (Box 249)
  - League of Nations Society in Canada, 1941 (Box 249)
  - The League of Nations Society of Haiti (Société Hatienne pour la Société des Nations), 1938 (Box 249)
  - League of Nations Union, 1930-1939 (Box 249)
  - League of Red Cross Societies, 1939-1945 (Box 249)
  - Liaison Committee for International Education, 1943-1945 (Box 249)
  - Masaryk Institute, 1937-1938 (Box 249)
  - Messages, 1931-1933 (Box 250)
  - Mid-West Council on International Affairs, 1935-1939 (Box 250)
  - Minnesota United Nations Committee, 1943-1947 (Box 250)
  - National Citizens Committee on the United Nations, 1948 (Box 250)
  - National Clearing House Committee, 1943 (Box 250)
  - National Committee on Atomic Information, 1946-1947 (Box 250)
  - National Committee on the Cause and Cure of War, 1941-1943 (Box 251)
  - National Committee on Post-War Immigration, 1945-1946 (Box 251)
  - National Committee of the United States of America on Intellectual Cooperation, 1938 1943-1946 (Box 251)
  - National Conference on Education and Citizenship, 1926 (Box 251)
  - National Council of American Soviet Friendship, Inc., 1945-1946 (Box 251)
  - National Council for the Prevention of War, 1925-1937 (Box 251)
  - National Council of Women, 1924-1931 (Box 251)
  - National Economic League, 1923-1924 (Box 251)
  - National Education Association, 1944-1947 (Box 251)
  - National Home Library Association, 1932-1933 (Box 252)
  - National Industrial Conference, 1926 (Box 252)
  - National League of Women Voters, 1924 1936-1938 (Box 252)
  - National Opinion Research Center, 1943-1945 (Box 252)
  - National Peace Conference, 1935-1945
    - 1935-1936 (Box 252)
    - 1937-1938 April (Box 253)
    - 1938 May -1945 (Box 254)
  - Miscellaneous publications (Box 254)
  - National Planning Association, 1942-1944 (Box 255)
  - National Policy Committee, 1941-1946 (Box 255)
  - National Student Forum on the Paris Pact, 1931 (Box 255)
  - National World Court Committee, 1931 (Box 255)
  - National Youth Administration, 1939 (Box 255)
  - Near East College Association, 1928-1929 (Box 255)
  - The New Commonwealth, 1936-1939 (Box 255)
  - New York State Citizens Council for a Durable Peace, 1943-1947
    - 1943-1944 (Box 255)
    - 1945-1947 (Box 256)
  - New York State Community Service Council, 1941-1944 (Box 256)